Peter Alan Tyler 我的父亲
Peter Alan Tyler, my dad.
世界上最了不起的人
The most wonderful man In the world.
生于1954年 9月15日
Born 15th September, 1954.
过来 Rose  到这儿来
Come here, Rose. Come here.
这是谁  是你爸爸
Who's that? It's your daddy.
他去世时你还太小 不记事
You weren't old enough to remember when he died.
1987年 11月7号
1987, 7th of November.
还记得我怎么给你说的吗
Do you remember what I told you?
就是Stuart Hoskins
The day that Stuart Hoskins
和Sarah Clark结婚的那天
and Sarah Clark got married.
他总是爱冒险
He was always having adventures.
啊 他看到现在的你会很高兴的
Ah, he would have loved to have seen you now.
妈妈总是对我这么说
That's what Mum always says.
所以我就想 我们能不能...
So I was thinking, could we...
我们能不能在我爸还活着的时候 去看看他
could we go and see my dad when he was still alive?
你怎么突然冒出这个念头了
Where's this come from all of a sudden?
好吧 如果不行的话
All right, if we can't,
如果违反了什么时间条例或者别的什么
if it goes against the laws of time or something,
别在意 忘了就是了
then never mind, just leave it.
没有啊 我能做任何事
No, I can do anything.
我只是更担心你罢了
I'm just more worried about you.
我想看看他
I want to see him.
你的心愿 即是我的使命
Your wish is my command.
不过可要小心许愿哦
But be careful what you wish for.
===BTM字幕组制作===
本字幕仅供学习 请勿商业使用
翻译:小十 匪 大牌
初校:CC  总校:遥若离
后期:Master
神秘博士
父之忌日
我 Peter Alan Tyler
I, Peter Alan Tyler,
愿娶
take you,
Jacqueline Andrea
Suzette Prentice
Suzette Prentice.
我 Peter Alan Tyler
I, Peter Alan Tyler,
愿娶 Jacqueline
take you, Jacqueline...
Susanne Suzette...
Susanne, Suzette...
Anita
Anita?
噢 就继续吧
Oh, just carry on.
戴安娜在结婚典礼时 将查理斯王子五个名字的顺序说颠倒了
这对戴安娜王妃来说够好的了
It's good enough for Lady Di.
我以为他会再高点儿的
I thought he'd be taller.
作为我的合法妻子
To be my lawful wedded wife.
相敬相爱 至死不渝
To love and behold till death us do part.
他死的时候离家很近
He died so close to home.
但我却不在场  没人在那儿
I wasn't there. Nobody was.
那司机肇事逃逸
It was a hit-and-run driver.
最后也没有查出来是谁
Never found out who.
当救护车赶到的时候他已经死了
He was dead when the ambulance got there.
我只希望 当时能有个人在那陪着他
I only wish there'd been someone there for him.
我希望成为他身边的那个人
I want to be that someone.
那样他就不会孤单死去了
So he doesn't die alone.
- 11月7日么   - 1987年
- November 7th? - 1987.
真不可思议
It's so weird.
我父亲去世的日子
The day my father died.
我还以为会有狂风暴雨什么的
I thought it'd be all sort of grim and stormy.
竟只是平常的一天
It's just an ordinary day.
过去就像是另一个国度
The past is another country.
1987年就像是怀特岛
1987 is just the Isle of Wight.
怀特岛 英格兰南部岛屿 历史悠久
- 你确定要去吗   - 确定
- You sure about this? - Yeah.
恶狼
就是这儿了  乔丹路
This is it. Jordan Road.
他迟到了
He was late.
他是去取结婚礼物 一个花瓶
He'd been to get a wedding present, a vase.
妈妈总是说 "那愚蠢的花瓶"
Mum always said, "That stupid vase."
他从车上下来
He got out of his car...
然后穿过马路
and crossed the road.
噢 天啊 就是现在了
Oh, God, this is it.
去他身旁  快点
Go to him. Quick.
现在太迟了
It's too late now.
救护车到的时候 他已经死了
By the time the ambulance got there, he was dead.
他不能一个人死去
He can't die on his own.
我能再试一次吗
Can I try again?
好了 那是第一次来的我和你
Right, that's the first you and me.
两对我们同时出现
It's a very bad idea,
这主意糟透了
two sets of us being here at the same time.
要小心 不能让他们看见我们
Just be careful they don't see us.
等她跑开 然后他跟过去了后
Wait till she runs off
你就去你爸爸身边
and he follows then go to your dad.
噢 天啊 就是现在了
Oh, God, this is it.
我做不到
I can't do this.
不必强迫自己做你不愿意的事情
You don't have to do anything you don't want to.
但这是我们最后一次能来这儿了
But this is the last time we can be here.
Rose 不行
Rose, no!
我成功了  我救了你的命
I did it. I saved your life.
我的乖乖 瞧见它那速度了么
Blimey, did you see the speed of it?
你记下他车牌号没
Did you get his number?
我真的成功了
I really did it.
噢 我的天 瞧你 你还活着
Oh, my God, look at you, you're alive.
那辆车本来能要你命的
That car was gonna kill you.
对我有点信心行吗 我已经看见那车过来了
Give me some credit, I did see it coming.
我总不会自己跑到轮子底下吧
I wasn't gonna walk under it, was I?
我叫Rose
I'm Rose.
真是巧了  我女儿也叫这个名字
That's a coincidence. That's my daughter's name.
那是个很棒的名字  选的不错  真好
That's a great name. Good choice. Well done.
好了  我得走了  我得去参加一场婚礼
Right. I better shift. I've got a wedding to go to.
是Sarah Clark的婚礼吗
Is that Sarah Clark's wedding?
对啊  你也是去参加的吗
Yeah. Are you going?
当然
Yeah.
你和你男朋友要搭便车么
Do you and your boyfriend need a lift?
好 我们到了 真抱歉啊 这里一团糟
Right, there we go, sorry about the mess.
如果想喝茶
If you want a cup of tea,
一直走过去就是厨房 牛奶在冰箱里
kitchen's down there, milk's in the fridge.
肯定在冰箱了 是吧  不然你还能放哪儿
It would be, wouldn't it? Where else would you put the milk?
说起来 还有外面的窗台
Mind you, there's always the windowsill outside.
我总是想如果有人发明了
I always thought if someone
带特殊隔间的窗台
invented a windowsill with special compartments,
你想啊 一格放牛奶 一格放酸奶
you know, one for milk, one for yoghurt,
就能赚大钱了
make a lot of money out of that.
能卖给学生 或者其他什么人
Sell it to students and things.
我该把这主意记下来
I should write that down.
总之 不管了  借过一下 我得去换件衣服
Anyway, never mind that. Excuse me, I got to go and change.
所有的东西妈妈都还留着  他的东西
All the stuff Mum kept. His stuff.
她把这些都装箱收藏在橱柜里
She kept it all packed away in boxes in the cupboard.
以前 她喝了酒之后就会给我看
She used to show me when she'd had a bit of drink.
都在这儿了 陈列在外
Here it is, on display.
这才是它们本该摆放的地方
Where it should be.
保龄球三等奖  前两名去了迪考镇玩
Third prize at the bowling. First two got to go to Didcot.
Didcot 迪考镇 隶属英国牛津郡
健康饮品
Health drinks.
妈妈以前管它们叫"滋补水"
Tonics.  Mum used to call them.
他就是靠买这些叫"急速X"的东西赚钱
He made his money selling this Vitex stuff.
他什么工作都做 非常聪明
He had all sorts of jobs, he was so clever.
太阳能供电  妈妈说他本来正要干这个的
Solar power. Mum said he was going to do this.
现在他可以继续了
Now he can.
好吧 我会告诉他你不是我男朋友的
Okay, I'll tell him you're not my boyfriend.
当我们相遇的时候 我说
When we met I said,
"和我一起在太空中旅行吧"
"Travel with me in space."
你说 "不"
You said, "No."
然后我说了"时间机器"
Then I said, "Time machine."
这并不是什么大阴谋
It wasn't some big plan.
我只是看着它发生了 然后我想
I just saw it happening, and I thought,
"我能够阻止它"
"I can stop it."
我又犯了一样的错
I did it again.
我又选了一只愚蠢的猿类
I picked another stupid ape.
我本应该知道的
I should have known.
这不是带你见识宇宙万物  从来都不是
It's not about showing you the universe. It never is.
而是宇宙万物为你做些什么
It's about the universe doing something for you.
那么说 你去其他时间里
So it's okay when you go
救别人的命时 就没问题
to other times and you save people's lives
而我救我爸爸 就不行了么
but not when it's me saving my dad?
我知道自己在做什么 而你不知道
I know what I'm doing, you don't.
两对我们同时出现 造成了时空上的脆弱点
Two sets of us being there made that a vulnerable point.
可是他还活着
But he's alive.
我的母星整个毁掉了 我所有的家人都不在了
My entire planet died, my whole family.
你以为我从没想过回到过去 拯救他们吗
Do you think it never occurred to me to go back and save them?
可是我又没有改变历史
But it's not like I've changed history.
起码改得不多  我是说
Not much. I mean,
他永远不会成为一个世界领袖
he's never gonna be a world leader,
他也不会发起第三次世界大战或别的什么
he's not gonna start World War III or anything.
Rose 现在世界上
Rose, there's a man alive in the world
活着一个从前不再活着的人
who wasn't alive before.
一个普通人  那就是茫茫世间最重要的存在
An ordinary man. That's the most important thing in creation.
整个世界都因他的存活而截然不同
The whole world's different because he's alive.
那你宁愿他死掉咯
So, would you rather him dead?
我没那么说...
I'm not saying that...
不 我明白了  就这一次
No, I get it. For once,
你不是我生命中最重要的那个人
you're not the most important man in my life.
那就看看没了我你怎么过吧  钥匙给我
Let's see how you get on without me. Give me the key.
Tardis的钥匙
The Tardis key.
如果我那么不重要 那就把钥匙还给我啊
If I'm so insignificant, give it me back.
行啊 我这就还你
All right then, I will.
你得到你想要的了 那么再见吧
You've got what you wanted so that's goodbye, then.
你才吓不着我
You don't scare me.
我知道你有多难过  你马上就会回来的
I know how sad you are. You'll be back in a minute.
或是在Tardis外徘徊着等我
Or you'll hang around outside the Tardis waiting for me.
我会让你等很久很久的
And I'll make you wait a long time.
和男朋友吵架了
Boyfriend trouble?
不好意思 介意我问一句么
Excuse me, would you mind?
你收拾这些干嘛
What are you tidying up for?
抱歉 成习惯了
Sorry, force of habit.
别担心他了  小两口吵架是常有的事
Don't worry about him. Couples have rows all the time.
我们不是一对儿
We're not a couple.
为什么所有人都认为我们是一对儿啊
Why does everyone think we're a couple?
我觉得他离开我了
I think he left me.
怎么会  像你这么漂亮的姑娘
What? A pretty girl like you?
如果我在和你约会的话...
If I was going out with you...
快别说了
Stop right there.
我只是说说而已
I'm just saying
我知道你说什么 我们不会往那方向发展
I know what you're saying and we're not going there.
任何情况下
At no point are we going
我们都不会往任何那附近的方向发展
anywhere near there.
你都不知道那方向究竟是哪个方向
You don't even know where that there exists...
我可不愿去想那方向
I don't want to think about there and,
相信我 你也不愿的
believe me, neither do you.
那方向 对你来说 就像...
There, for you, is like...
就像百慕大三角区
like the Bermuda Triangle.
老天 你可真会恭维人
Blimey, you know how to flatter a bloke.
好了  我们出发吧
Right. Are we off?
那么 这不是什么模糊的暗示信号咯
So, that wouldn't be a mixed signal at all?
绝对不是
Absolutely not.
我真该把你送回你该住的疯人院去
I'll take you back to the loony bin where you belong.
但我肯定之前在哪儿见过你
Except I'm sure I've met you somewhere before.
- 真奇怪   - 咋了
- It's weird. - What?
这么多人都缺席了
There's so many people missing.
Steven叔叔 Lynn阿姨
Uncle Steven, Auntie Lynn,
还有Baxter全家
all the Baxters.
他们都去哪儿了
Where are they?
你不觉得出什么事了吗
You don't think something's gone wrong?
可能这是个天赐良机 让你有时间再考虑考虑
Maybe it's a godsend, gives you time to think.
你不用非得结婚 至少如今不用了
You don't have to go through with it, not these days.
- 先未婚同居一段儿试试   - 爸啊
- Live in sin for a bit. - Dad.
10年后 你会后悔 你会说
In 10 years' time, you'll turn round and say,
真希望我能让时间倒流啊
"If only I could turn the clock back."
是我自己的感觉吗 还是真的变冷了
Is it me or did it just get cold?
Rose
Rose.
电台音乐: Never Gonna Give You Up 永不放弃你 1987年 Rick Astley演唱
我在赛马的时候遇到这个家伙
I met this bloke at the horses
*我想告诉你我的感觉*
*I just wanna tell you how I'm feeling*
他在版权上分我一点油水
and he's cutting me in on copyright.
我还以为你是个正经商人
But I thought you were a proper businessman in there.
*Gotta make you understand*
*我永不放弃你 永远不让你失望*
我也希望啊  我做点儿这 做点儿那
I wish. I do a bit of this, bit of that.
维持生计嘛
I scrape by.
*Never gonna give you up, never gonna let you down*
*永远不会弃你而去*
好吧  那一定是我听错了
Right. I must've heard wrong.
所以 实际上 你是个油嘴滑舌的家伙
So, really, you're a bit of a Del Boy.
*Never gonna run around and desert you*
*永不让你哭泣 永不与你别离*
Del Boy是BBC情景喜剧"Only Fools And Horses"中狡猾而讨喜的人物
你就使劲批判我吧
Shoot me down in flames.
*Never gonna make you cry, never gonna say goodbye*
*永不用谎言伤害你*
你和我老婆不会有点血缘关系吧
You're not related to my wife by any chance, are you?
噢 天啊  她也会在婚礼上
Oh, my God. She's gonna be at the wedding.
*Never gonna tell a lie and hurt you*
*我们相识许久*
Jackie  你认识她吗
Jackie? Do you know her?
*你隐隐心痛 只是羞于启齿*
*Your heart's been aching but you're too shy to say it*
算是吧
Sort of.
那她怎么跟你说我的
What's she told you about me, then?
她说她挑到了世界上最棒的男人
She said she'd picked the most fantastic man in the world.
*我们心中都知道是什么...*
*Inside we both know what''s been...*
那一定是别的Jackie了
Must be a different Jackie, then.
她可永远都不会那么说的
She'd never say that.
电台歌曲: The Street 2003年
这玩意真让我头疼
This stuff goes right over my head.
- 这还没发行呢   - 哼 干的好
- That's not out yet. - Good job and all.
我查下短信
I'm just gonna check my messages.
短信 什么意思
How do you mean? Messages?
- 那是个电话吗   - 嗯
- Is that a phone? - Yeah.
Watson 过来  我需要你
Watson, come here. I need you.
1876年3月10日 贝尔发明电话后测试时打给助手的第一句话
Watson 过来  我需要你
Watson, come here. I need you.
Watson 过来 我需要你
一半的宾客还没有露面
Half the guests haven't turned up.
还好你不在这儿
You're better off not being here,
这简直是一场正在形成的灾难
it's a disaster in the making.
不 在这种情况下
No, in this case,
"奉子成婚"正是我会用的词
"Knocked her up" Is a phrase I'd use.
Watson 过来 我需要你
Watson, come here. I need you.
1876年3月10日 贝尔发明电话后测试时打给助手的第一句话
喂 你是谁
Hello? Who's this?
Watson 过来 我
Watson, come here. I...
爸爸 进来吧
Dad, get inside.
我们在婚礼之前不能见到新娘
We can't see the bride before the wedding.
会带来厄运的
That's bad luck.
你遇见她那天就是厄运了
Bad luck when you met her.
我跟你说 今天算是被诅咒了
I tell you, this day is cursed.
看啊 这才称得上是甜美的白色蓬蓬裙
Now that's what I call a meringue.
meringue 蛋白酥 蛋白与糖打发烘制的蓬松甜点
Stuart的父亲说
Stuart's dad said go round
去街区兜一圈看看吧 因为有人消失了
the block 'cause there's people missing.
你说"消失了"是什么意思
How do you mean, missing?
Dave Sunita Bee都没出现
There's no Dave, no Sunita, no Bee...
羔羊旗帜酒吧也没人来
There's no one from The Lamb and Flag.
我的裙子又开了
My train's detached again.
我就知道我该用个尼龙搭扣的
I knew I should have used Velcro.
有我在呢 不用抱怨了
I'm here, stop your bellyaching.
抱Rose一会儿 可以吗
Take Rose a sec, will you?
她难道不可爱吗
Ain't she pretty?
她是个小美女 美极了
She's a little madam, that's what she is.
我需要一些帮手
I need more hands.
她那没用的老爹去哪里了
Where's her useless article of a dad got to?
爸
Dad!
是那辆车 和之前是同一辆
It's that car. Same one as before.
就在我们面前 他去哪了
It was right in front of us, where's he gone?
你刚才叫我"爸"了  为什么
You called me "Dad"? What did you say that for?
奥 太棒了 老出事故的家伙
Oh, wonderful! Here he is, the accident waiting to happen.
估计你连自己的葬礼都会迟到
You'd be late for your own funeral
刚刚差不多就是了
and it nearly was.
- 我没受伤   - 这又是谁
- No damage done.   - And who's this?
嘴张这么大 看什么呢
What are you looking at with your mouth open?
- 你的头发   - 什么
- Your hair.   - What?
我还从来没有见过这样的
I've never seen it like...
我是说
I mean...
很好看 你的头发很好看
it's lovely, your hair's lovely.
你抱着的那个孩子
And that baby you're holding.
一定就是你的孩子吧
That would be your baby.
又是你在哪勾搭到的姑娘吧
Another one of yours, is she?
她救了我的命
She saved my life.
这回挺新鲜  上次是什么来着
That's a new one. What was it last time?
我甚至都不认识她  那是个衣帽间服务员
I didn't even know her. She was a cloakroom attendant.
我当时在帮她找我的票
I was helping her look for my ticket.
有三件一模一样的风帽粗呢大衣
There were three duffle coats all the same.
不知怎的 衣架倒了
Somehow the rack collapsed.
我们就被压在那堆东西下面了
We were under all this stuff.
你是不是总拈花惹草啊
Were you playing around?
他干了什么和你有关系吗
What's it got to do with you what he gets up to?
- 他到底干了什么   - 你心里明白
- What does he get up to?   - You'd know.
我那么傻吗
Because I'm that stupid.
我风流完了还把她带回来见老婆
I play around and I bring her to meet the missus.
- 你个蠢牛   - 你就有那么蠢
- You silly cow.   - But you are that stupid.
我们能回家再吵吗 先消停一会儿
Can we keep this stuff for back home, just for now?
什么 在那个垃圾堆里吗
What, with the rest of the rubbish?
你把打折的清洁剂 滋补水
You bring home cut-price detergents, tonic water,
大号录像带拿回家 没一样有用的
Betamax tapes and none of it works.
我都快在你的垃圾里淹死了
I'm drowning in your rubbish.
他是怎么跟你说的  说他是个大商人吗
What did he tell you? Did he say he's this big businessman?
他根本不是  他是个失败者
Cause he's not. He's a failure.
天生没用种 那个家伙
Born failure, that one.
Rose需要一个称职的父亲
Rose needs a proper father...
Jackie 我在辛苦赚钱
Jackie, I'm making a living.
我们能有饭吃 不是吗
It keeps us fed, doesn't it?
够了
Stop it.
你们俩不是这样的  你们彼此相爱啊
You're not like this. You love each other.
Pete 你以前可不喜欢疯疯癫癫的姑娘啊
Pete, you never used to like them mental.
或者我不知道 也许你喜欢呢
Or I don't know, maybe you did.
Jackie 等等 听我说
Jackie, wait, listen...
你给我小心点
If you're not careful,
否则今天结婚离婚一块办
there'll be a wedding and a divorce on the same day.
在这儿等一下  给我几分钟和我老婆谈谈
Wait here. Give us a couple of minutes with the missus.
这样吧 你去把车停好
Tell you what, straighten the car up.
停在街角附近
Stick it round the corner.
不要再惹麻烦
Don't cause any more trouble.
嘿 Jack
Hey, Jack.
我不想听 又是粗呢大衣什么的 换汤不换药
I'm not listening. It's the duffle coats all over again.
Jackie 有时候粗呢大衣只是粗呢大衣
Jackie, sometimes a duffle coat is just a duffle coat.
很快一切都会好起来的 我保证
Things will get better soon. I promise.
我受够你的愚蠢计划了
I've had enough of all your daft schemes.
吃完上顿没下顿
I never know where the next meal's coming from.
我会解决的 亲爱的
I'll get it right, love.
很快就会有那天 我向你保证 我会解决的
One day soon, I promise you I'll get it right.
乐观点
Come on.
怪物 它们要吃我们
Monsters! Going to eat us!
什么怪物啊 亲爱的 是外星人吗
What sort of monsters, sweetheart? Is it aliens?
Rose
Rose!
进教堂里去
Get in the church!
上帝啊 它们是什么
Oh, my God. What are they?
进去
Inside!
- Sarah   - 待在那别动
- Sarah! - Stay in there!
进去
In.
它们进不来的 这些门窗都有年头了 好了
They can't get in. Old windows and doors. Okay.
越古老 越坚固
The older something is, the stronger it is.
还能做什么
What else?
去检查一下其他的门 快
Go and check the other doors. Move!
怎么回事 那些是什么 到底是什么
What's happening? What are they? What are they?
时间遭遇了事故 出现了裂缝
There's been an accident in time. A wound in time.
就像细菌 乘隙而入
They're like bacteria, taking advantage.
你说的时间是什么意思
What do you mean? Time?
你在念叨什么 什么时间
What are you jabbering on about time?
我早知道你会喋喋不休
I might've known you'd argue.
Jackie 你总在抱怨 烦死了
Jackie, I'm sick of you complaining.
你是怎么知道我的名字的
How do you know my name?
我从来没有见过你
I've never met you in my life.
我不解决这个问题 你就没机会见到我了
You never will unless I sort this out.
如果你不介意的话 我老早就想这么说了
If you don't mind, I've waited a long time to say this,
Jackie Tyler 我说啥你做啥
Jackie Tyler, do as I say.
去检查那些门
Go and check the doors.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
我早该那么做了
I should've done that ages ago.
- 我爸爸在外面   - 待会儿再默哀吧
- My dad was out there. - You can mourn him later.
现在我们要集中注意力保命
Now we've got to concentrate on keeping ourselves alive.
- 我爸爸已经   - 我对此无能为力
- My dad had... - There is nothing I can do for him.
不是 但他有个叫手机的东西
No, but he had this phone thing.
它不管用了 我一直收到这个声音
I can't get it to work. I keep getting this voice.
Watson 过来 我需要你
Watson, come here. I need you.
这是人类史上第一个电话
That's the very first phone call.
Watson 过来 我需要你
Watson, come here. I need you.
来自亚历山大 格雷厄姆 贝尔
Alexander Graham Bell.
我觉得这个电话不会派上多大用场
I don't think the telephone's gonna be much use.
一定有人叫了警察了
Someone must have called the police.
警察也帮不了你们 没有人可以
The police can't help you now, no one can.
宇宙中的任何东西都无法伤害那些怪物
Nothing in this universe can harm those things.
时间被损坏了 它们是来修补裂缝的
Time's been damaged and they've come to sterilise the wound.
以消灭所有可见事物的方式
By consuming everything inside.
这是因为
Is this because...
是我的错吗
Is this my fault?
不要啊
No!
城市上空有烟升起 却没听见警报
There's smoke coming up from the city. But no sirens.
我觉得不只是我们这里
I don't think it's just us.
这些东西肯定是到处都是
I think these things are all over the place.
可能是全世界
Maybe the whole world.
那是辆车吧
Was that a car?
那不重要 不用担心
It's not important. Don't worry about it.
你的那个同伴 他说是你的错 是什么意思
This mate of yours. What did he mean, this is your fault?
不知道 所有事吧
Don't know. Just everything.
我把我的车钥匙给了你
I gave you my car keys.
人们不会把车钥匙给一个完全陌生的人
You don't give your keys to a complete stranger.
这就 就像我很信任你
It's like I trusted you.
从我遇见你的时候起 就信任你
The moment I met you, I just did.
时间裂痕
A wound in time.
你叫我爸
You called me Dad.
我看得出来
I can see it.
你有我的眼睛
My eyes.
Jackie的气势
Jackie's attitude.
你大喊时听起来很像她
You sound like her when you shout.
你是 你是 你是我的Rose
You are. You are. You're my Rose.
你是我的Rose 长大的Rose
You're my Rose, grown up.
爸爸  我爸爸  我的爸爸
Dad! My dad. My daddy.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
- 先生   - 博士
- Mister?   - Doctor.
你好像了解状况
You seem to know what's going on.
我总是给人那种印象 没错
I give that impression, yeah.
- 我只是想问问   - 你能救我们吗
- I just wanted to ask...   - Can you save us?
你们是谁呢
Who are you two, then?
Stuart Hoskins
Stuart Hoskins.
Sarah Clark
Sarah Clark.
还有一个呢  男孩还是女孩
And one extra? Boy or girl?
我不知道  其实 我也不想知道
I don't know. I don't want to know, really.
你们两个是怎么开始的
How did all this get started?
在Beatbox俱乐部的外面 凌晨两点
Outside the Beatbox Club, 2:00 in the morning.
街角处 我钱包丢了 没有打出租车的钱
Street corner, I'd lost my purse, didn't have money for a taxi.
- 我送她回的家   - 然后呢
- I took her home. - Then what?
约她了?
Asked her for a date?
他把他的电话号码写在我手背上
Wrote his number on the back of my hand.
从此就再也甩不掉她啦
Never got rid of her since.
我爸爸说
My dad said...
我不知道这是怎么回事
I don't know what this is
我也知道我们无足轻重
all about and I know we're not important...
谁说你们无足轻重
Who said you're not important?
我去各种地方游历过
I've travelled to all sorts of places,
做过的事你们根本无法想像
done things you couldn't even imagine.
但是你们两个
But you two.
街角处 凌晨两点 坐出租车回家
Street corner, 2:00 in the morning, getting a taxi home.
我从未经历那样的生活
I've never had a life like that.
是的
Yes.
我会尽力救你们的
I'll try and save you.
我是个爸爸了
I'm a dad.
我是说 我已经是个爸爸了
I mean, I'm already a dad
但是是Rose长大了 长成了你
but Rose grows up and she's you.
太好了
That's wonderful.
我是说 我还以为你会没什么出息呢
I mean, I suppose I thought that you'd be a bit useless
因为遗传了我的无用基因 但是
what with my useless genes and all but...
你是怎么到这来的
Well, how did you get here?
- 你真想知道吗   - 是啊
- Do you really want to know?   - Yeah.
时光机器
A time machine.
- 时光机器吗   - 我发誓是真的
- Time machine? - Cross my heart.
你来的时候 人们都有时光机器了么
Do you all have time machines where you come from?
不是 只有博士有
No, just the Doctor.
你早就知道这些怪物会出现吗
Did you know these things were coming?
不知道
No.
上帝啊 我不知道 我的头好晕啊
God, I don't know, my head's spinning.
未来是什么样子的
What's the future like?
和现在没多大区别
It's not so different.
我是什么样子的 我的头发灰了吗
What am I like? Have I gone grey?
我秃顶了吗 别告诉我我秃顶了
Have I gone bald? Don't tell me I've gone bald.
那么 如果你这朋友不是你男朋友
So, if this mate of yours isn't your boyfriend,
我得说我很高兴
and I have to say I'm glad
因为作为你的爸爸
cause being your dad and all,
我觉得他对你来说有点老了
I think he's a bit old for you.
你有男朋友了吗
Have you got a bloke?
没有 以前有过
No. I did have.
Mickey
Mickey.
你认识他吗
Do you know him?
他穿了西装我没认出来
I just didn't recognise him in a suit.
你得放开我 亲爱的
You have to let go of me, sweetheart.
我老这么对他说
I'm always saying that.
他逮谁抱谁
He just grabs hold of what's passing
抱住就不松手
and holds on for dear life.
上帝快帮帮他女朋友吧
God help his poor girlfriend
如果他能找到一个的话
if he ever gets one.
我和Rose只是在聊天
Me and Rose were just talking.
哦 是吗 聊天啊
Oh, yeah? Talking?
世界末日了 你在干嘛呢
While the world comes to an end, what do you do?
和最年轻的金发美女依依相惜
Cling to the youngest blonde.
走吧 Mick
Come on, Mick.
- 你不能告诉她   - 为什么
- You can't tell her. - Why?
我是说 我真的不希望你告诉她
I mean, I really don't want you to tell her.
- 你不想让人知道吗   - 我来的时候
- You don't want people to know? - Where I come from,
Jackie还不知道怎么用
Jackie doesn't know how to work
录像机的计时器呢
the timer on the video recorder.
我上周还教过她
I showed her that last week.
我懂了
Point taken.
Rose
Rose,
你不会带来世界末日
you're not going to bring about the end of the world, are you?
是吧
Are you?
Jackie让我照看好她
Jackie gave her to me to look after.
这情况似曾相识啊
How times change.
我最好小心点儿
I'd better be careful.
我想Mickey刚刚认准我了
I think I just imprinted myself on Mickey
印随行为 一些动物跟随着它所见到的第一个移动的物体并当做母亲的行为
像小鸡找妈妈一样
like a mother chicken.
别  别碰婴儿
No. Don't touch the baby.
你们俩是同一个人 这是悖论
You're both the same person, that's a paradox.
我们可不希望悖论出现
We don't want a paradox happening,
外面那些鬼东西还在张牙舞爪呢
not with these things outside.
任何新状况 任何时间上的波动
Anything new, any disturbance in time,
都会使它们更强大
makes them stronger.
一个悖论就可能把它们放进来
A paradox might let them in.
我什么事都做不好 是吧
I can't do anything right, can I?
既然你都问了 没错  所以 别碰婴儿
Since you asked, no. So, don't touch the baby.
我又不是白痴
I'm not stupid.
你都能把我耍的团团转了
You could have fooled me.
好吧
All right...
对不起
I'm sorry.
我没真想丢下你
I wasn't really gonna leave you on your own.
我知道
I know.
我也就告诉你 我还没想出计划
Between you and me, I haven't got a plan.
不知如何是好
No idea.
无路可走
No way out.
你会想出办法的
You'll think of something.
整个地球都已经被清洗了
The entire Earth's been sterilised.
这里 还有在像这里的其他地方里躲着的
This, and other places like it,
是仅剩的人类了
are all that's left of the human race.
我们也许能撑一阵子
We might hold out for a while,
但没什么能阻止这些生物
but nothing can stop those creatures.
最终 它们还是能进来
They'll get through in the end.
这些建筑还不够古老
The walls aren't that old.
我根本无法阻止它们
And there's nothing I can do to stop them.
曾经有律法
There used to be laws
阻止这类情况发生
stopping this kind of thing from happening.
我的族人能阻止这一切
My people would have stopped this.
但他们都不在了
But they're all gone.
而现在 我也快随他们而去了
And now I'm going the same way.
如果我意识到
If I'd realised...
只要
Just...
跟我说对不起
tell me you're sorry.
对不起
I am.
真的对不起
I'm sorry.
你身上有什么在发烫
Have you got something hot?
是Tardis的钥匙
It's the Tardis key.
这说明它还跟Tardis相连
It's telling me it's still connected to the Tardis.
我飞船的内部被抛出时空裂缝了
The inside of my ship was thrown out of the wound
但我们可以用这个来把它带回来
but we can use this to bring it back.
只要取回我的飞船 我就可以恢复一切
And once I've got my ship back, then I can mend everything.
现在 我只需要一点能量  哪位有电池
Now, I just need a bit of power. Has anybody got a battery?
这个够大吗
This one big enough?
太好了
Fantastic.
感谢老爸  给你
Good old Dad. There you go.
只要充一点电就好
Just need to do a bit of charging up.
然后就能把所有人带回来了
And then we can bring everyone back.
你 呃 你一直没说 为什么要来到这里
You, erm, you never said why you came here in the first place.
如果我有时光机
If I had a time machine,
我不会觉得1987年有什么特别的
I wouldn't have thought 1987 was anything special.
至少这里没什么特别的
Not round here, anyway.
我们只是刚好到了这里
We just ended up here.
那我可真幸运啊 是吧
Lucky for me, eh?
如果你没到这儿救我
If you hadn't been there to save me...
那只是个巧合
That was just a coincidence.
那可真的是好运啊  真奇妙
That was just really good luck. It's amazing.
那 在未来 我和我内人还在一起吗
So, in the future, are me and her indoors still together?
嗯
Yeah.
- 你还和我们住在一起吗   - 是的
- You still living with us? - Yep.
我是个好爸爸吗
Am I a good dad?
你...
You...
我小时候 你每晚都给我讲睡前故事
You told me a bedtime story every night when I was small.
你一直都在 你一晚上都没错过
You were always there, you never missed one.
还有 嗯...
And, erm...
每个周六你都带我们到乡下野餐
you took us for picnics in the country every Saturday.
你从来没让我们失望
You never let us down.
你始终和我们在一起
You were there for us all the time.
是我真正的依靠
Someone I could really rely on.
那不是我
That's not me.
好了 谁也别碰那钥匙
Right, no one touches that key,
都听到了吗  别碰那钥匙
have you got that? Don't touch it.
要是有人碰了那钥匙
Anyone touches that key,
链接就会 恩 嘎嘣断了
it'll be, well, zap!
只要顺其自然 一切都会好起来的
Just leave it be and everything will be fine.
我们都能出去  所有人
We'll get out. All of us.
Stuart Sarah 你们俩会结婚的
Stuart, Sarah, you're gonna get married,
我说会就一定会
just like I said.
当时间理顺了
When time gets sorted out...
每个人都会忘记发生的一切
Everybody here forgets what happened.
别担心 你改变的事情不会再变回去
And don't worry, the thing that you changed will stay changed.
你是说我还是会活着
You mean I'll still be alive.
而我本来应该死了
Though I'm meant to be dead.
这就是为什么我此生毫无作为
That's why I haven't done anything with my life.
此生毫无意义
Why it didn't mean anything.
- 不是这样的   - 扯淡
- Doesn't work like that. - Rubbish.
我太没用了 甚至都不能好好去死
I was so useless I couldn't even die properly.
发生的这一切 都是我的错
Now it's my fault all this has happened.
- 这是我的错   - 不 亲爱的
- This is my fault. - No, love.
我是你父亲
I'm your dad.
作为一个父亲 就要负起担当错误的责任
It's my job for it to be my fault.
她父亲  你怎么会是她父亲
Her dad? How are you her dad?
你那时才几岁  12岁
How old were you? 12?
- 噢 真恶心   - Jacks 听着
- Oh, that's disgusting. - Jacks, listen.
- 她是Rose   - Rose?
- This is Rose. - Rose?
你恶不恶心啊
How sick is that?
你给我女儿取了个二手名字吗
Did you give my daughter a second-hand name?
你有多少风流债啊
How many are there?
你都管她们叫Rose吗
Do you call them all Rose?
啊 天呐 瞧  她们是同一个Rose
Oh, for God's sake, look. It's the same Rose.
Rose 不
Rose, no!
大家到我身后去
Everyone, behind me!
我是这里最古老的
I'm the oldest thing in here.
博士
Doctor!
它凉了
It's cold.
这钥匙是凉了
The key's cold.
噢 我的天啊 他死了
Oh, my God, he's dead.
这全都是我的错
This is all my fault.
你们两个 你们所有人
Both of you, all of you.
整个世界
The whole world.
完了  我们无能为力  都结束了
This is it. There's nothing we can do. It's the end.
博士真的很在乎你
The Doctor really cared about you.
他不想你再承受一次
He didn't want you to go through it again.
只要还有别的办法
Not if there was another way.
但现在没有了
Now there isn't.
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
那辆本该撞死我的车 亲爱的
The car that should have killed me, love.
它在这儿了
It's here.
博士早就明白了 但他...
The Doctor worked it out way back but he...
他试图保护我
tried to protect me.
但是
Still.
现在他不能负责了
He's not in charge anymore.
我说了算
I am.
- 但你不能   - 我是谁 亲爱的
- But you can't. - Who am I, love?
我爸爸
My daddy.
Jackie 看看她
Jackie, look at her.
她是我们的女儿
She's ours.
当然
Of course.
我本就该去死的 Jackie
I'm meant to be dead, Jackie.
你终究摆脱了我
You're gonna get rid of me at last.
别这么说
Don't say that.
仅此一次 相信我  这是注定的
For once in your life, trust me. It's got to be done.
你要活下去
You've got to survive
因为你还要把我们的女儿养大成人
cause you've got to bring up our daughter.
我从没给你读过睡前故事
I never read you those bedtime stories,
我从没带你们去野餐过
I never took you on those picnics.
我从来都不在你身旁
I was never there for you.
你本应在的
You would've been.
但我能为你做这个
But I can do this for you.
现在 我能为你做一个称职的父亲了
I can be a proper dad to you now.
但这不公平
But it's not fair.
我已经多活好几个小时了
I've had all these extra hours.
这世界上没人有过这么好的待遇
No one else in the world has ever had that.
最重要的是 我见到了你
And on top of that, I get to see you.
你真漂亮
And you're beautiful.
我是多么幸运啊 是吧
How lucky am I, eh?
所以 来吧  按爸爸说的做
So, come on. Do as your dad says.
你会陪着我吧 亲爱的
You gonna be there for me, love?
谢谢你救了我
Thanks for saving me.
再见 亲爱的
Goodbye, love.
去见他最后一面  快
Go to him. Quick.
那司机还只是个孩子
The driver was just a kid.
他停下了 等着警察到来
He stopped, he waited for the police.
不是他的错
It wasn't his fault.
不知为何 Pete自己跑了出去
For some reason, Pete just ran out.
有人说 有一个女孩
People say there was this girl.
在他垂死之际 她一直陪着他
And she sat with Pete while he was dying.
她握着他的手
She held his hand.
然后就离开了
Then she was gone.
没人知道那女孩是谁
Never found out who she was.
Peter Alan Tyler
Peter Alan Tyler,
我的父亲
my dad.
世界上最了不起的男人
The most wonderful man in the world.
死于1897年 11月7日
Died 7th November, 1987.
神秘博士
下集预告
那我们为什么追它
And why are we chasing it?
这是紫色的 很危险
It's mauve and dangerous,
而且是30秒前从伦敦市中心发射的
and about 30 seconds from the centre of London.
Rose
Rose!
请让我进去 妈咪
Please let me in, Mummy.
千万别让他碰你
You mustn't let him touch you.
- 你是个医生吗   - 也算在行
- Are you a doctor? - I have my moments.
他们的伤都是一样的
They've all got the same injuries.
连手背上的伤疤都是一样的
Right down to the scar on the back of the hand.
物理性损伤 如同瘟疫
Physical injuries as plague.
- 你好   - 你好
- Hello. - Hello.
在阳台喝一杯怎么样
Shall we have a drink on the balcony?
我喜欢把自己当成罪犯
I like to think of myself as a criminal.
我猜也是
I bet you do.